Contact

tomhiatt@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/tomhiatt-8180b037 (LinkedIn)

Top Skills

R (Programming Language)
R Shiny
Presentation Skills

Languages

English (Native or Bilingual)
Tagalog (Full Professional)
French (Limited Working)

Tom Hiatt

Digital Health Expert at the World Health Organization Manila, National Capital Region, Philippines

Summary

Digital Health Expert providing applied solutions in eHealth, mHealth, infectious diseases, health emergencies, data visualization, country development, effective social interventions, and social business/ enterprise in various countries (Armenia, Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Mongolia, Papua New Guinea, Philippines, Romania, Switzerland, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan, Viet Nam, Zimbabwe).

Portfolio: http://bit.ly/tomhiatt

Experience

World Health Organization 18 years 9 months

TB specialist September 2023 - Present (2 years 1 month) Philippines

Deploying the latest developments and technologies with the Philippines Department of Health to find, detect and treat the 750 thousand annual tuberculosis cases every year, and to prevent families, friends and health workers from the disease.

Public Health Specialist June 2022 - August 2023 (1 year 3 months) Toshkent, Uzbekistan

Implementing effective interventions for the National TB Programmes of 5 Central Asia countries - Kazakhstan, Kyrgyzstan, Tajikistan, Turkmenistan, Uzbekistan.

Public Health Specialist, Tuberculosis & Rabies May 2019 - June 2022 (3 years 2 months) Manila, Philippines

Supported massive scale-up of tuberculosis (TB) screening, testing, treatment and prevention under the Race to End TB campaign resulting in a 15% year-on-year increase in cases found.

Developed and designed four mobile apps for the End TB App Suite (http://ntp.doh.gov.ph/apps) - CARE TB for supporting patient care; RACE TB for surveillance and monitoring; LEAD TB for programmatic management; and GUIDE TB for eLearning and eReference. Also developed the COVID-19 surveillance system, COVIDKAYA.

Supported the National Rabies Prevention and Control Program with joint annual reports from the human and animal sectors, improved data flows, technical advisories, national vaccination campaigns, a rapid response toolkit, and health promotion.

Created the contact tracing handbook to support the national COVID-19 response.

Monitoring And Evaluation Specialist, Health Emergencies January 2017 - June 2019 (2 years 6 months) Manila, Philippines

Created an internal implementation monitoring systems to ensure effective results-based activities were conducted according to the WHO Planning, Budgeting and Monitoring Framework.

Planned and conducted a training workshop on After Action Reviews and Simulation Exercises.

Created an M&E database to collect and store all M&E activities under the IHR Monitoring and Evaluation Framework as well as National Action Plans and Pandemic Preparedness Plans.

Epidemiologist, Tuberculosis and Leprosy January 2012 - December 2016 (5 years) Manila, Philippines

Led the analysis and data visualization development for eight annual global TB control reports (2007 to 2014 datasets).

Conducted in-depth TB programme reviews in Viet Nam, Mongolia, Papua New Guinea and the Philippines to assess progress and recommend improvements for Ministries of Health.

Developed mobile apps for TB and leprosy including programme directory and leprosy disability assessment tool with high user acceptance.

Health Data Analyst, Tuberculosis January 2007 - January 2012 (5 years 1 month)

Geneva Area, Switzerland

Created four Global TB control reports as part of core writing team (www.who.int/tb/publications/global_report). Led data management and analysis for "Improving TB estimates" workshops in all 6 WHO regions.

Taught 10 plus trainings for the WHO Health Data Forum for over 100 global health professionals on data analysis and visualization. Conceptualized redesign of order management system for Global Drug Facility. Designed TB technical assistance coordination web tool.

Education

London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, U. of London MSc, Epidemiology · (2010 - 2013)

Brigham Young University
BA, Visual art, Media art · (2001 - 2005)